In ancient Greece,
في اليونان القديمة،
when anyone from slaves to soldiers, poets and politicians,
عندما يكون أي شخص من العبيد وحتى الجنود والشعراء والسياسيين
needed to make a big decision on life's most important questions,
يحتاجون لاتخاذ قرار حاسم في أسئلة الحياة الهامة.
like, "Should I get married?"
مثل: "هل من اللازم أن أتزوج؟"
or "Should we embark on this voyage?"
أو"هل يجب أن نشرع في هذه الرحلة؟"
or "Should our army advance into this territory?"
"هل يجب أن يتقدم جيشنا نحو هذه الأرض؟"
they all consulted the oracle.
جميعهم استشار الأوراكل (الوسيطة الروحية).
So this is how it worked:
فهكذا سار الأمر:
you would bring her a question and you would get on your knees,
أن تسألها سؤالاً وتركع
and then she would go into this trance.
ثم ستنتقل هي إلى حالة من النشوة.
It would take a couple of days,
وقد يستغرق هذا يومين
and then eventually she would come out of it,
ولتخرج في النهاية
giving you her predictions as your answer.
وتعطيك تنبؤاتها بمثابة إجابة لأسئلتك.
From the oracle bones of ancient China
من عظام الوسيط الروحي للصين القديمة
to ancient Greece to Mayan calendars,
إلى اليونان القديمة وتقويمات المايا،
people have craved for prophecy
يتشوق الأشخاص إلى التوقعات
in order to find out what's going to happen next.
حتى يكتشفوا ما ينتظرهم مستقبلاً.
And that's because we all want to make the right decision.
وذلك لأننا جميعاً نرغب في اتخاذ القرار الصحيح.
We don't want to miss something.
لا نريد أن يفوتنا شيئًا.
The future is scary,
فالمستقبل مُخيف،
so it's much nicer knowing that we can make a decision
لذا فمن الأجمل معرفة أننا يمكننا اتخاذ قرار
with some assurance of the outcome.
مع بعض الضمانات للنتائج.
Well, we have a new oracle,
حسناً، لدينا أوراكل جديد
and it's name is big data,
واسمه هو البيانات الضخمة،
or we call it "Watson" or "deep learning" or "neural net."
أو نسميه نحن "واتسون" أو"التعليم العميق" أو"الشبكة العصبية الاصطناعية."
And these are the kinds of questions we ask of our oracle now,
وهذه أنواع من الأسئلة التي نطرحها الآن على أوراكل،
like, "What's the most efficient way to ship these phones
مثل "ما هي أفضل وسيلة لنقل الهواتف بحريًا
from China to Sweden?"
من الصين إلى السويد؟"
Or, "What are the odds
أو "ما هو احتمال
of my child being born with a genetic disorder?"
أن يولد طفلي باضطراب وراثي؟"
Or, "What are the sales volume we can predict for this product?"
أو "ما هو حجم المبيعات المتوقع لهذا المنتج؟"
I have a dog. Her name is Elle, and she hates the rain.
لدي كلبة تُدعى إيل، وتكره المطر.
And I have tried everything to untrain her.
جربت كل شيء لأصرفها عن هذا الإحساس.
But because I have failed at this,
ولكن لأنني فشلت في ذلك،
I also have to consult an oracle, called Dark Sky,
فأنا مضطرة إلى استشارة أوراكل يدعى "دارك سكاي"
every time before we go on a walk,
في كل مرة نذهب في نزهة
for very accurate weather predictions in the next 10 minutes.
للحصول على تنبؤات دقيقة عن حالة الطقس في العشر دقائق القادمة.
She's so sweet.
إنها لطيفة للغاية.
So because of all of this, our oracle is a $122 billion industry.
وبسبب كل ذلك، يمثل وسيطنا الروحي قطاعًا تجاريًا بحجم 122 مليار دولاراً.
Now, despite the size of this industry,
حاليًا، على الرغم من حجم هذه الصناعة،
the returns are surprisingly low.
فالأرباح منخفضة بشكل غير متوقع.
Investing in big data is easy,
إن الاستثمار في البيانات الضخمة يسير
but using it is hard.
ولكن استخدامها صعبًا.
Over 73 percent of big data projects aren't even profitable,
أكثر من 73% من مشروعات البيانات الضخمة غير مربحة.
and I have executives coming up to me saying,
يقول لي رؤساء تنفيذيون
"We're experiencing the same thing.
"إننا نعيش نفس التجربة.
We invested in some big data system,
استثمرنا في مجال البيانات الضخمة
and our employees aren't making better decisions.
ولا يتخذ الموظفون لدينا قرارات أفضل.
And they're certainly not coming up with more breakthrough ideas."
وبالتأكيد ليس لديهم المزيد من الأفكار المبدعة."
So this is all really interesting to me,
هذا مثير للاهتمام بالنسبة لي
because I'm a technology ethnographer.
لأنني عالمة في مجال الأعراق البشرية التكنولوجية.
I study and I advise companies
أنا أدرس وأنصح الشركات
on the patterns of how people use technology,
بأنماط استخدام الناس للتكنولوجيا،
and one of my interest areas is data.
والبيانات هي إحدى مجالات إهتمامي.
So why is having more data not helping us make better decisions,
فلماذا لا يساعدنا المزيد من البيانات على اتخاذ قرارات أفضل،
especially for companies who have all these resources
خاصة الشركات التي لديها جميع تلك المصادر
to invest in these big data systems?
للاستثمار في أنظمة البيانات الضخمة؟
Why isn't it getting any easier for them?
لماذا لا يسهل الأمر عليهم؟
So, I've witnessed the struggle firsthand.
لذلك شاهدت الصراع لأول مرة.
In 2009, I started a research position with Nokia.
في عام 2009 بدأت بحثًا مع نوكيا.
And at the time,
في ذلك الوقت،
Nokia was one of the largest cell phone companies in the world,
كانت نوكيا إحدى كبرى شركات الهاتف الخلوي في العالم،
dominating emerging markets like China, Mexico and India --
وكانت تسيطر على الأسواق الناشئة، مثل: الصين والمكسيك والهند--
all places where I had done a lot of research
كل الأماكن التي قمت بها بالكثير من الأبحاث
on how low-income people use technology.
عن كيفية استخدام ذوي الدخل المنخفض للتكنولوجيا.
And I spent a lot of extra time in China
قضيت الكثير من الوقت الإضافي في الصين
getting to know the informal economy.
لكي أعرف الاقتصاد غير الرسمي.
So I did things like working as a street vendor
فقمت ببعض الأمور، مثل بائعة متجولة
selling dumplings to construction workers.
كنت أبيع معجنات لعمال البناء.
Or I did fieldwork,
وقمت بأعمال في الحقول،
spending nights and days in internet cafés,
قضيت أيامًا وليال في مقاهي الإنترنت،
hanging out with Chinese youth, so I could understand
وتنزهت مع بعض الشباب الصينيين لكي أفهم
how they were using games and mobile phones
كيف كانوا يستخدمون الألعاب والهواتف الخلوية
and using it between moving from the rural areas to the cities.
واستخدامها أثناء التنقل من المناطق الريفية إلى المدن.
Through all of this qualitative evidence that I was gathering,
من خلال نوعية الأدلة تلك التي كنت أجمعها،
I was starting to see so clearly
بدأت ألاحظ بوضوح
that a big change was about to happen among low-income Chinese people.
أن تغيرًا كبيرًا كان على وشك الحدوث بين الصينيين ذوي الدخل المنخفض.
Even though they were surrounded by advertisements for luxury products
على الرغم من إعلانات السلع الكمالية التي كانت تحاوطهم،
like fancy toilets -- who wouldn't want one? --
مثل المراحيض الفاخرة -- من لا يريد امتلاك واحد؟ --
and apartments and cars,
والشقق السكنية والسيارات،
through my conversations with them,
من خلال محادثاتي معهم
I found out that the ads the actually enticed them the most
وجدت أن الإعلانات التي كانت تجذبهم بشدة
were the ones for iPhones,
هي إعلانات أجهزة الآي فون
promising them this entry into this high-tech life.
التي تعدهم بدخول هذا العالم من التقنية العالية.
And even when I was living with them in urban slums like this one,
وحتى عندما كنت أعيش معهم في عشوائيات بالمدينة مثل هذه،
I saw people investing over half of their monthly income
رأيت الناس تستثمر أكثر من نصف دخلها الشهري
into buying a phone,
في شراء هاتف خلوي
and increasingly, they were "shanzhai,"
وكانت تلك الهواتف من نوع "shanzhai"
which are affordable knock-offs of iPhones and other brands.
وهي هواتف مقلدة من الآي فون وغيرها من الماركات.
They're very usable.
كانت صالحة للاستخدام.
Does the job.
تقوم بمهامها.
And after years of living with migrants and working with them
بعد عدة سنوات من العيش مع مهاجرين والعمل معهم
and just really doing everything that they were doing,
والقيام بكل شيء يفعلونه،
I started piecing all these data points together --
بدأت جمع تلك البيانات جميعها معًا --
from the things that seem random, like me selling dumplings,
بداية من الأشياء التي تبدو عشوائية مثل بيع المعجنات
to the things that were more obvious,
إلى الأشياء الأكثر وضوحًا،
like tracking how much they were spending on their cell phone bills.
مثل متابعة ما ينفقونه علي فواتير هواتفهم المحمولة.
And I was able to create this much more holistic picture
وكنت قادرة على خلق تلك الصورة الشمولية
of what was happening.
عما كان يحدث.
And that's when I started to realize
وهنا عندما بدأت أن أدرك
that even the poorest in China would want a smartphone,
أن حتى أفقر الصينيين يريدون هواتف ذكية،
and that they would do almost anything to get their hands on one.
وسيفعلون أي شيء ليحصلوا عليها.
You have to keep in mind,
يجب أن تعرف أن
iPhones had just come out, it was 2009,
أجهزة الأي فون ظهرت عام 2009
so this was, like, eight years ago,
أي منذ ثماني سنوات
and Androids had just started looking like iPhones.
وبدأت أجهزة الأندرويد تبدو كالآي فون.
And a lot of very smart and realistic people said,
ويقول الكثير من الناس الذكية والواقعية
"Those smartphones -- that's just a fad.
"إن الهواتف الذكية مجرد صيحة."
Who wants to carry around these heavy things
"من يريد اقتناء مثل تلك الأشياء الثقيلة"
where batteries drain quickly and they break every time you drop them?"
"حيث تتعطل البطاريات سريعًا، وتنكسر الهواتف عندما تسقط منك"
But I had a lot of data,
ولكن كان لدى بياناتٌ عدة
and I was very confident about my insights,
وكنت واثقة جدًا من رؤيتي.
so I was very excited to share them with Nokia.
لذلك كنت متحمسة للغاية لأشاركها مع نوكيا.
But Nokia was not convinced,
ولكن نوكيا لم تقتنع،
because it wasn't big data.
لأنها لم تكن بيانات ضخمة.
They said, "We have millions of data points,
وقالوا "لدينا الملايين من نقاط البيانات"
and we don't see any indicators of anyone wanting to buy a smartphone,
ولا نرى أية مؤشرات تتنبأ عن أي شخص يريد شراء هاتف ذكي
and your data set of 100, as diverse as it is, is too weak
ومجموعة بياناتك المتنوعة كليًا ضعيفة للغاية بالنسبة لنا
for us to even take seriously."
لنأخذها على محمل الجد.
And I said, "Nokia, you're right.
وقلت لهم" لديك حق يا نوكيا"
Of course you wouldn't see this,
"بالتأكيد لن تروا ذلك،"
because you're sending out surveys assuming that people don't know
لأنكم تصدرون الدراسات وتفترضون أن الناس لا تعرف
what a smartphone is,
ما هو الهاتف الذكي،
so of course you're not going to get any data back
ولذلك لن تستقبلوا أية بيانات في المقابل
about people wanting to buy a smartphone in two years.
عن الراغبين في هاتف لمدة عامين.
Your surveys, your methods have been designed
صممتم أبحاثكم وأساليبكم
to optimize an existing business model,
لتتفاءلوا بنموذج أعمال مثير للاهتمام،
and I'm looking at these emergent human dynamics
وأنا أنظر لتلك الديناميكا البشرية الناشئة
that haven't happened yet.
التي لم تحدث بعد.
We're looking outside of market dynamics
نحن ننظر خارج ديناميكيات الأسواق
so that we can get ahead of it."
حتى نستطيع أن نبعد عنها."
Well, you know what happened to Nokia?
حسنًا، هل تعلمون ماذا حدث لنوكيا؟
Their business fell off a cliff.
كسد نشاطها التجاري.
This -- this is the cost of missing something.
هذا مقابل إغفال شيء ما.
It was unfathomable.
كان الأمر مبهمًا.
But Nokia's not alone.
ولكن نوكيا ليست وحدها هكذا.
I see organizations throwing out data all the time
أرى مؤسسات تتجاهل البيانات طوال الوقت
because it didn't come from a quant model
لأنها لم تنتج عن نموذج كمي
or it doesn't fit in one.
أو لا تتناسب مع واحدٍ.
But it's not big data's fault.
ولكنه ليس خطأ البيانات الضخمة.
It's the way we use big data; it's our responsibility.
ولكن الخطأ يوجد في طريقة استخدامها، فهذه مسؤوليتنا.
Big data's reputation for success
إن سمعة نجاح البيانات الضخمة
comes from quantifying very specific environments,
تأتي من قياس بيئات محددة جدًا،
like electricity power grids or delivery logistics or genetic code,
مثل شبكات الطاقة الكهربائية أو التسليم اللوجيستي أو الشفرة الجينية
when we're quantifying in systems that are more or less contained.
عندما نحدد المقدار في الأنظمة المتضمنة.
But not all systems are as neatly contained.
ولكن ليست كل الأنظمة تشارك بدقة.
When you're quantifying and systems are more dynamic,
عندما تقيس، وتكون الأنظمة أكثر ديناميكية
especially systems that involve human beings,
وخاصة الأنظمة التي تتضمن بشرًا،
forces are complex and unpredictable,
القوى معقدة وغير متوقعة،
and these are things that we don't know how to model so well.
وهذه أشياء لا نستطيع إعمالها بشكل جيد.
Once you predict something about human behavior,
عندما تتوقع شيئًا عن سلوك الإنسان
new factors emerge,
تظهر عوامل أخرى
because conditions are constantly changing.
لأن الظروف تتغير باستمرار.
That's why it's a never-ending cycle.
ولذلك فهي دورة لا تنتهي.
You think you know something,
تعتقد أنك تعلم أمرًا،
and then something unknown enters the picture.
وبعد ذلك يظهر شيء غير معلوم في الصورة.
And that's why just relying on big data alone
لذلك الاعتماد على البيانات الضخمة وحدها
increases the chance that we'll miss something,
يزيد فرصة إغفال شيء ما،
while giving us this illusion that we already know everything.
في الوقت الذي يتهيأ لنا أننا نعرف بالفعل كل شيء.
And what makes it really hard to see this paradox
وما يجعل من الصعب رؤية هذه المفارقة
and even wrap our brains around it
وحتي يركز انتباهنا عليه
is that we have this thing that I call the quantification bias,
هو أن لدينا ما أُسميه الانحياز الكمي،
which is the unconscious belief of valuing the measurable
وهوالاعتقاد اللاإرادي بتصديق ما يمكن قياسه
over the immeasurable.
عن ما لا يمكن قياسه.
And we often experience this at our work.
وغالبًا ما نواجه ذلك في عملنا.
Maybe we work alongside colleagues who are like this,
من الممكن أن نعمل بجانب زملاء هكذا
or even our whole entire company may be like this,
أو أن تكون الشركة بأكملها مثل ذلك
where people become so fixated on that number,
حيث يصبح الناس مركزين انتباههم على الأرقام
that they can't see anything outside of it,
إلى أن يتعذر عليهم رؤية أي شيء بدونها،
even when you present them evidence right in front of their face.
حتى لو وضعت الدليل مباشرةً أمام أعينهم.
And this is a very appealing message,
وهذه رسالة رائعة،
because there's nothing wrong with quantifying;
لأنه لا يوجد عيب في القياس
it's actually very satisfying.
فهو في الواقع مُرضٍ.
I get a great sense of comfort from looking at an Excel spreadsheet,
ينتابني إحساس كبير بالراحة عند النظر في جدول بيانات على برنامج إكسل
even very simple ones.
حتى الجداول البسيطة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's just kind of like,
فالأمر مثل
"Yes! The formula worked. It's all OK. Everything is under control."
"حسنًا! نجحت المعادلة. كل شيء على ما يرام."
But the problem is
ولكن المشكلة هي
that quantifying is addictive.
أن القياس إدماني.
And when we forget that
وعندما ننسى ذلك
and when we don't have something to kind of keep that in check,
وعندما لا نملك ما نستطيع التأكد منه
it's very easy to just throw out data
من السهل إلقاء البيانات جانبًا
because it can't be expressed as a numerical value.
لأنه لا يمكن ترجمتها كقيمة رقمية.
It's very easy just to slip into silver-bullet thinking,
من اليسير اللجوء للتفكير السهل
as if some simple solution existed.
كأنه يوجد حل بسيط بالفعل.
Because this is a great moment of danger for any organization,
ولأن هذه لحظة خطر لأية مؤسسة
because oftentimes, the future we need to predict --
ولأن في معظم الوقت نحتاج إلى التنبؤ بالمستقبل --
it isn't in that haystack,
فهو ليس إبرة في كومة قش،
but it's that tornado that's bearing down on us
ولكنه ينقض علينا كالثور الهائج
outside of the barn.
الخارج من الحظيرة.
There is no greater risk
لا يوجد شيء
than being blind to the unknown.
أخطر من كونك مسلِّمًا بالمجهول.
It can cause you to make the wrong decisions.
يمكن أن يجعلك ذلك تتخذ قرارات خاطئة.
It can cause you to miss something big.
يمكن أن تغفل شيئًا مهمًا،
But we don't have to go down this path.
ولكن لسنا مضطرين أن نسلك هذا الدرب.
It turns out that the oracle of ancient Greece
اتضح أن الوسيطة الروحية في اليونان القديمة
holds the secret key that shows us the path forward.
تمتلك المفتاح السري الذي يرينا الطريق للأمام.
Now, recent geological research has shown
والآن أوضح بحث جيولوجي حديث
that the Temple of Apollo, where the most famous oracle sat,
أن معبد أبولو حيث جلست الوسيطة الروحية الأشهر،
was actually built over two earthquake faults.
كان مبنيًا فوق صدعين زلزاليين.
And these faults would release these petrochemical fumes
وبعث الصدعان تلك الأبخرة البتروكيماوية
from underneath the Earth's crust,
الموجودة تحت القشرة الأرضية
and the oracle literally sat right above these faults,
وجلست الوسيطة حرفيًا فوق الصدعين مباشرةً
inhaling enormous amounts of ethylene gas, these fissures.
مستنشقة كميات ضخمة من غاز الإيثيلين، هذان الصدعان.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's true.
هذا حقيقي.
It's all true, and that's what made her babble and hallucinate
هذا ما جعلها تخرج الفقاقيع
and go into this trance-like state.
وتدخل في هذه الحالة من النشوة.
She was high as a kite!
كانت منتشية للغاية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So how did anyone --
كيف استطاع أي شخص..
How did anyone get any useful advice out of her
كيف استطاع أي شخص أن يأخذ منها نصيحة
in this state?
في هذه الحالة؟
Well, you see those people surrounding the oracle?
حسنًا، هل ترون هؤلاء المحيطين بالوسيطة الروحية؟
You see those people holding her up,
ترون الأشخاص الذين يرفعونها لأعلى
because she's, like, a little woozy?
لأنها كالمشوشة الذهن قليلًا؟
And you see that guy on your left-hand side
هل ترون الرجل تجاه اليسار
holding the orange notebook?
الممسك بالدفتر البرتقالي؟
Well, those were the temple guides,
هؤلاء كانوا مرشدي المعبد،
and they worked hand in hand with the oracle.
وتعاونوا مع الوسيطة الروحية.
When inquisitors would come and get on their knees,
عندما يأتي الباحثون عن الحقيقة ويركعون أمامها،
that's when the temple guides would get to work,
يبدأ مرشدو المعبد عملهم،
because after they asked her questions,
لأن بعد سؤالها أسئلتهم
they would observe their emotional state,
سيراقبون حالاتهم الشعورية
and then they would ask them follow-up questions,
وسيطلبون منهم إجابة الأسئلة
like, "Why do you want to know this prophecy? Who are you?
مثل " لماذا تريد أن تعرف هذه النبؤة؟ من أنت؟"
What are you going to do with this information?"
" ماذا تنوي أن تفعل بهذه المعلومة؟"
And then the temple guides would take this more ethnographic,
يأخذ مرشدو المعبد هذا على محمل علم الأعراق البشرية.
this more qualitative information,
تلك المعلومات الكمية
and interpret the oracle's babblings.
ويفسرون فقاعات الوسيطة الروحية.
So the oracle didn't stand alone,
حتى لا تعمل الوسيطة بمفردها،
and neither should our big data systems.
وكذلك أنظمة البيانات الضخمة خاصتنا.
Now to be clear,
وحتى أكون واضحة،
I'm not saying that big data systems are huffing ethylene gas,
لا أعني أن الأنظمة تبعث غاز الإيثيلين
or that they're even giving invalid predictions.
أو أنها تعطي تنبؤات غير صحيحة،
The total opposite.
بل على العكس.
But what I am saying
ولكن ما أقوله هو أن
is that in the same way that the oracle needed her temple guides,
كما احتاجت الوسيطة الروحية لمرشدي المعبد
our big data systems need them, too.
تحتاج أنظمة البيانات الضخمة أيضا لهم.
They need people like ethnographers and user researchers
تحتاج أشخاص كعلماء الأعراق البشرية
who can gather what I call thick data.
الذين يستطيعون جمع ما أسميه البيانات الكثيفة.
This is precious data from humans,
هذه بيانات عن البشر لا تقدر بثمن
like stories, emotions and interactions that cannot be quantified.
مثل القصص و المشاعر والتفاعلات التي لا يمكن قياسها.
It's the kind of data that I collected for Nokia
هذه هي فئة البيانات التي جمعتها لنوكيا
that comes in in the form of a very small sample size,
التي تكون في حجم عينة صغيرة للغاية،
but delivers incredible depth of meaning.
ولكن توصل عمقًا هائلًا من المعنى.
And what makes it so thick and meaty
والذي يجعلها كثيفة وغنية
is the experience of understanding the human narrative.
هي خبرة فهم الرواية الإنسانية.
And that's what helps to see what's missing in our models.
وهذا ما يساعد على رؤية المفقود في نماذجنا.
Thick data grounds our business questions in human questions,
تبنى البيانات الكثيفة أسئلة نشاطنا التجاري على أسئلة الناس.
and that's why integrating big and thick data
ولذلك تكامل البيانات الضخمة والبيانات الكثيفة
forms a more complete picture.
يُكون صورةً كاملةً.
Big data is able to offer insights at scale
تستطيع البيانات الضخمة تقديم وجهات نظرعلى قدر ما هو مطلوب
and leverage the best of machine intelligence,
وتدعم عمل أفضل الماكينات
whereas thick data can help us rescue the context loss
ولكن البيانات الكثيفة تساعد في إنقاذ السياق المفقود
that comes from making big data usable,
الذي يأتي من جعل البيانات الضخمة صالحة للاستعمال
and leverage the best of human intelligence.
وتدعم ذكاء البشر.
And when you actually integrate the two, that's when things get really fun,
عندما تدمج الاثنين، تصبح الأمور أكثر مرحًا
because then you're no longer just working with data
لأنك لم تعد تعمل مع البيانات فقط
you've already collected.
التي قد جمعتها بالفعل.
You get to also work with data that hasn't been collected.
أنت مضطر للعمل مع البيانات التي لم تجمعها بعد.
You get to ask questions about why:
ستسأل أسئلة عن:
Why is this happening?
لماذا يحدث هذا؟
Now, when Netflix did this,
عندما فعلت شركة نتفليكس هذا،
they unlocked a whole new way to transform their business.
فتحوا طريقًا جديدًا لتغيير نشاطهم التجاري.
Netflix is known for their really great recommendation algorithm,
تُعرف نتفليكس بخوارزمية اقتراحات رائعة،
and they had this $1 million prize for anyone who could improve it.
وقد قدمت جائزة بقيمة مليون دولار لمن يستطيع تحسينها.
And there were winners.
وكان يوجد فائزون.
But Netflix discovered the improvements were only incremental.
ولكن وجدت نتفليكس أن الاقتراحات كانت تزايدية فقط.
So to really find out what was going on,
وحتى تتأكد أنها تتقدم
they hired an ethnographer, Grant McCracken,
عينت العالم في وصف الأعراق البشرية، غرانت مكراكين،
to gather thick data insights.
لجمع وجهات نظر البيانات الضخمة.
And what he discovered was something that they hadn't seen initially
وما اكتشفه كان شيئًا لم يروه في البداية
in the quantitative data.
في البيانات الكمية.
He discovered that people loved to binge-watch.
اكتشف أن الناس أحبت الإفراط في المشاهدة.
In fact, people didn't even feel guilty about it.
في الواقع المشاهدون لم يشعروا بالذنب لذلك.
They enjoyed it.
ولكن استمتعوا به.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So Netflix was like, "Oh. This is a new insight."
كان لسان حال نتفليكس: "هذا رأي جديد".
So they went to their data science team,
لذلك ذهبت لفريقها العلمي
and they were able to scale this big data insight
واستطاعوا قياس هذا المنظور
in with their quantitative data.
من البيانات الضخمة مع البيانات الكمية.
And once they verified it and validated it,
وعندما تأكدوا من ذلك
Netflix decided to do something very simple but impactful.
قررت نتفليكس عمل شيء بسيط، ولكنه مؤثر.
They said, instead of offering the same show from different genres
فقالوا بدلًا من عرض نفس البرنامج من فئات مختلفة
or more of the different shows from similar users,
أو برامج أكثر من مستخدمين متشابهين،
we'll just offer more of the same show.
سنعرض حلقات أكثر من نفس البرنامج.
We'll make it easier for you to binge-watch.
سنجعل فكرة مشاهدة عدة حلقات مسلسلة أسهل.
And they didn't stop there.
ولم تتوقف عند ذلك.
They did all these things
فعلوا كل هذه الأشياء
to redesign their entire viewer experience,
لإعادة تشكيل خبرة المشاهد كلها
to really encourage binge-watching.
لتشجيع فكرة المشاهدة التسلسلية.
It's why people and friends disappear for whole weekends at a time,
هذا سبب اختفاء الناس والأصدقاء في العطلات الأسبوعية.
catching up on shows like "Master of None."
لمتابعة البرامج مثل "ماستر أوف نن".
By integrating big data and thick data, they not only improved their business,
استطاعت تحسين عملها بدمج البيانات الضخمة مع البيانات الكثيفة
but they transformed how we consume media.
ولكنها غيرت طريقة استهلاكنا للإعلام.
And now their stocks are projected to double in the next few years.
والآن من المتوقع أن تتضاعف مبيعاتهم في السنوات القليلة القادمة.
But this isn't just about watching more videos
ولكن هذا ليس فقط عن مشاهدة المزيد من الفيديوهات
or selling more smartphones.
أو بيع المزيد من الهواتف الذكية.
For some, integrating thick data insights into the algorithm
بالنسبة للبعض، إدماج البيانات الكثيفة في خوارزمياتهم
could mean life or death,
قد يعني حياة أو موت،
especially for the marginalized.
خاصة للمهمشين.
All around the country, police departments are using big data
تستخدم أقسام الشرطة في كل أنحاء الدولة البيانات الضخمة
for predictive policing,
لضبط الأمن التنبؤي
to set bond amounts and sentencing recommendations
لكي تضع أرقامًا للسندات واقتراحات للعقوبة
in ways that reinforce existing biases.
بطرق تعزز الانحياز الموجود.
NSA's Skynet machine learning algorithm
إن خوارزمية التعلم الآلي (سكاي نت) لدى الأمن القومي الأمريكي
has possibly aided in the deaths of thousands of civilians in Pakistan
أدت إلى وفاة آلاف المواطنين في باكستان
from misreading cellular device metadata.
نتيجة سوء قراءة البيانات الوصفية للجهاز الخلوي.
As all of our lives become more automated,
ولأن حياتنا أصبحت أكثر آلية
from automobiles to health insurance or to employment,
من السيارات حتى التأمين الصحي أو التوظيف
it is likely that all of us
فعلى الأرجح أن جميعنا
will be impacted by the quantification bias.
سيتأثر بالانحياز القياسي.
Now, the good news is that we've come a long way
والآن، الخبر الجيد هو أننا سلكنا طريقًا طويلًا
from huffing ethylene gas to make predictions.
من استنشاق غاز الايثيلين إلى صنع التنبؤات.
We have better tools, so let's just use them better.
لدينا أدوات أفضل، فهيا نستخدمها بشكل أفضل.
Let's integrate the big data with the thick data.
لندمج البيانات الضخمة مع البيانات الكثيفة.
Let's bring our temple guides with the oracles,
لِنُحضر مرشدي المعبد مع الوسيطة الروحية،
and whether this work happens in companies or nonprofits
وسواء إذا كان هذا العمل داخل شركات أو جمعيات غير حكومية
or government or even in the software,
أو الحكومة أو حتي في البرمجيات،
all of it matters,
كل ذلك مهم،
because that means we're collectively committed
لأنه يعني أننا ملتزمون بشكل جماعي
to making better data,
لصنع بيانات أفضل
better algorithms, better outputs
وخوارزميات ونتائج أفضل
and better decisions.
وقرارات أفضل.
This is how we'll avoid missing that something.
هكذا سنتجنب إغفال ذلك الشيء.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)